# Eric Fischer

# ericmfischer.com

# **Background**

**Purpose**: I'm a Ph.D. student with a specialization in natural language processing from the Department of Statistics at the University of California, Los Angeles. I perform research on energy-based generative models applied to language problems at the Center for Vision, Cognition, Learning, and Autonomy at UCLA. My advisors are Dr. Ying Nian Wu and Dr. Song-Chun Zhu.

I earned a Master of Science from the Department of Computer Science at UCLA, submitting a thesis *Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference* (escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw). A deep generative classifier uses Short Run Markov Chain Monte Carlo inference, Langevin dynamics, and backpropagation through time to achieve similar classification accuracy as an analogous discriminative classifier, i.e., a convolutional neural network, while it has the advantages that it can generate data, it can learn unsupervised with additional *unlabeled* data, and it exhibits robustness to adversarial attacks due to the stochasticity of the Langevin equation and the top-down architecture of the underlying generator network.

**Research Interests**: Natural Language Processing, Computer Vision, Representation Learning, Generative Models, Unsupervised Learning, Energy-Based Models

## Education

## University of California, Los Angeles | Ph.D. Statistics

Sep 2020 - current

• Specialization: natural language processing

#### University of California, Los Angeles | M.S. Computer Science

Sep 2018 - June 2020

- Specialization: artificial intelligence
- Thesis: Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference (escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw)

## University of California, Los Angeles | B.A. Philosophy

Sep 2009 - June 2013

- Philosophy Departmental Honors, UCLA College Honors, Cum Laude Honors
- Emphasis in philosophy of language and propositional and first-order logic

## **Publications**

# Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference | M.S. Thesis | escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw

• Deep generative classifier uses Short Run Markov Chain Monte Carlo inference, Langevin dynamics, and backpropagation through time to achieve similar classification accuracy as an analogous discriminative classifier, i.e., a convolutional neural network, while it has the advantages that it can generate data, it can learn unsupervised with additional *unlabeled* data, and it exhibits robustness to adversarial attacks due to the stochasticity of the Langevin equation and the top-down architecture of the underlying generator network

# Learning Multi-Layer Latent Variable Model via Variational Optimization of Short Run MCMC for Approximate Inference | arxiv.org/pdf/1912.01909.pdf | ECCV | contributor (not author)

• Short Run MCMC residual network outperforms a variational autoencoder in terms of image reconstruction error and image synthesis quality, while not requiring the design of a separate inference network

#### Research

#### Exact and Cluster Sampling of Ising Model | github.com/EricMFischer/exact-and-cluster-sampling-markov-chains

 A convergence analysis comparing exact sampling, using the Gibbs sampler and coupled Markov chains, to cluster sampling, using the Swendsen-Wang algorithm

#### First-Order Optimization Methods for CNN | github.com/EricMFischer/first-order-nn-optimization

• Custom Python implementations and convergence analyses of first-order optimization methods Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD), SGD with momentum, SGD with Nesterov momentum, RMSprop, and Adam

## T-Snake Model for Generative Inpainting | github.com/CS269-Capstone/t-snake-mask-generation

• Employs a topology adaptive snake deformable model to probabilistically generate missing image data

#### Variational Lower Bound Formulation and Application of VAE | github.com/EricMFischer/variational-autoencoder

• Statistical formulation and analysis of evidence lower bound for the variational autoencoder, using the MNIST dataset

# **Experience**

Center for Vision, Cognition, Learning, and Autonomy | Graduate Researcher | Los Angeles, CA | Dec 2018 - current

• Perform research on energy-based generative models applied to language problems

## University of California, Los Angeles | Teaching Assistant | Los Angeles, CA

Mar 2020 - current

Have served as a Teaching Assistant and Grader for many undergraduate and graduate statistics courses at UCLA

#### eXp Realty | South Bay Association of Realtors | Realtor | Los Angeles, CA

Nov 2021 - current

- Realtor for eXp Realty, the fastest-growing real estate brokerage in the world
- Department of Real Estate license ID: 02042145
- Email: eric.fischer@exprealty.com

## NatureBox | Full Stack Software Engineer | Redwood City, CA

Mar 2016 - Dec 2017

- Core contributor to new Flux/React web application created after company added direct-to-consumer business
- Led various projects including a payment processor migration, addition of Amazon payments, and a 2<sup>nd</sup> version of API

# Cinemagram | Software Engineer | San Francisco, CA

Sep 2015 - Dec 2015

• Worked with Python, Ruby, and SQL code to construct internal data management interfaces and tools

#### ClearPath Capital Partners | Wealth Advisor Associate | San Francisco, CA

Sep 2013 - June 2014

• Earned Series 65 (Uniform Investment Adviser Law Exam) license to act as an investment advisor in California

#### **Graduate Coursework**

# University of California, Los Angeles

STATS 200A - Applied Probability

STATS 200B - Theoretical Statistics (winter 2023)

STATS 200C - High Dimensional Statistics (spring 2023)

STATS 201A - Research Design, Sampling, and Analysis (in progress)

**STATS 201B** - *Statistical Modeling and Learning* (winter 2023)

STATS 201C - Advanced Modeling and Inference

STATS 202A - Statistics Programming (in progress)

STATS 202B - Matrix Algebra and Optimization

STATS 202C - Monte Carlo Methods for Optimization

COM SCI M276A / STATS M231A - Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning

COM SCI M266A / STATS M232A - Statistical Modeling and Learning in Vision and Cognition (audited)

COM SCI M266B / STATS M232B - Statistical Computing and Inference in Vision and Cognition

COM SCI 247 - Advanced Data Mining

COM SCI 251A - Advanced Computer Architecture

COM SCI 269 - Seminar in Artificial Intelligence: Deformable Models

EC ENGR M235 - Modern Environmental Statistics (spring 2023)

EC ENGR 236C - Optimization for Large-Scale Systems

EC ENGR 239AS - Neural Networks and Deep Learning

EC ENGR C243A - Neural Signal Processing (audited, spring 2023)

#### Independent

Hack Reactor, Advanced Software Engineering Immersive Program, San Francisco, CA, <a href="https://hackreactor.com">hackreactor.com</a>, June - Sep 2015 CS 224n - Natural Language Processing with Deep Learning, Stanford University on <a href="https://www.web.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/">web.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/</a> CS 230 - Deep Learning, Stanford University on <a href="https://www.cs230.stanford.edu">cs230.stanford.edu</a>

CS 231n - Deep Learning for Computer Vision, Stanford University on cs231n.stanford.edu

Wrote two chapters and edited several others of two textbooks authored by my Ph.D. advisors Dr. Song-Chun Zhu and Dr. Ying Nian Wu, which summarize over 20 years of artificial intelligence research at UCLA: *Statistical Models for Marr's Paradigm* (ericmfischer.com/publication/book-1/book-1.pdf) and *Stochastic Grammars for Scene Parsing* (ericmfischer.com/publication/book-2/book-2.pdf)